Blair and Lee Family Papers, 1640-1946 (bulk 1812-1920 ): Finding Aid C0614
Manuscripts Division
Blair and Lee Family Papers
1640-1946
1812-1920
Manuscripts Division
Blair family.
C0614
253 linear feet 477 boxes
The collection consists of the personal and family papers of five members of the Blair and Lee families of Maryland, Washington, D.C., and Virginia -- Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876); his daughter, Elizabeth Blair Lee (1818-1906); her husband, Samuel Phillips Lee (1812-1897); their son, Blair Lee (1857-1944, Princeton Class of 1880); and his cousin, Andrew Alexander Blair (1848-1932) -- reflecting their various political, journalistic, naval, family, business, legal, and domestic interests.
Biographical / Historical
Biography of Francis Preston Blair
Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876), journalist and politician, was born in Abingdon, Virginia, and raised in Kentucky. His grandfather, John Blair, held the first chair in theology at Princeton University. He graduated from Transylvania University in 1811 and married Eliza Violet Gist (1733-1877) a year later. Blair was admitted to the bar in 1817 but never practiced law. He became interested in Kentucky politics joining the New Court party and aiding his political ally, Amos Kendall, in editing the Argus of Western America and the Patriot in Frankfort. Blair became an advocate of Andrew Jackson, and on the advice of Kendall, Jackson called him to Washington in 1830 to become editor of the Globe, which became the official newspaper of the administration. A loyal Jacksonian, Blair was a confidential member of the Kitchen Cabinet and served Jackson faithfully from 1830 through 1837. The Globe continued to be a powerful voice through the Van Buren administration (1837-1841). Blair was forced to resign in 1845 by the new president, James K. Polk.
Retiring to his country estate, Silver Spring, in Maryland, Blair continued to exercise political power and influence, often through his sons, Francis "Frank" Preston (1821-1875) and Montgomery (1813-1883).
Biography of Samuel Phillips Lee
Samuel Phillips Lee (1812-1897), an officer in the United States Navy, was born in Fairfax, Virginia, the son of Francis Lightfoot Lee, grandson of Richard Henry Lee, and great nephew of Francis Lightfoot Lee, both signers of the Declaration of Independence. In 1825 he was appointed a midshipman and proceeded to work his way through the ranks, becoming a rear-admiral in 1870. When commanding the Dolphin in 1851, Lee was employed in coastal survey duty making deep-sea soundings, testing currents, and searching for shallow ocean spots. His report of this work, The Cruise of the Dolphin (1854), was of considerable help to Matthew F. Maury, the oceanographer. During the Civil War, Lee remained loyal to the Union and participated in the Charleston blockade, the attack on New Orleans, and the battle of Vicksburg, and commanded both the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron and the Mississippi Squadron. After the war, he served at various posts, and his last command was as head of the North Atlantic fleet (1870-1872). In 1873 he retired from the navy.
While a young officer, Lee courted Elizabeth Blair Lee (1818-1906), the only daughter of Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876). After a lengthy courtship, Elizabeth Blair and Samuel Phillips Lee were married in 1843. Their only child, (Francis Preston) Blair Lee, was born in 1857. The family lived in Washington and at Silver Spring, Maryland, the country estate of Francis Preston Blair. After his retirement from the navy, Lee ran the day-to-day activities of the farm, and it was there that he died in 1897.
Biography of Elizabeth Blair Lee
Elizabeth Blair Lee (1818-1906), the only daughter of Francis Preston Blair and Eliza Violet Gist Blair, grew up in Washington, D.C., and Silver Spring, Maryland, immersed in the politics of the day. A favorite of Andrew Jackson, "Lizzie" lived in the White House for a time to please him. After she married Samuel Phillips Lee, a naval officer, in 1843, she often wrote to him keeping him up to date not only on family matters but also on local and national politics. She actively gathered this information through the comments of her father, editor of the Democratic organ, the Globe, and her brothers, Montgomery Blair, postmaster general under Lincoln, and Francis "Frank" Preston Blair, Jr., a general in the Civil War. Her political role also included serving as her father's amanuensis and sometime ghostwriter of his speeches.
Aside from being an avid follower of the political scene, Elizabeth Blair Lee spent much of her time raising her only child, (Francis Preston) Blair Lee, born in 1857; meeting the obligations of a large extended family; and participating in the busy social scene in Washington and Maryland. She also served for many years as a director of the Washington City Orphan Asylum. In 1906, Elizabeth Blair Lee died at Silver Spring where she had lived with her son and his family.
Biography of Andrew Alexander Blair
Andrew Alexander Blair (1848-1932), son of Francis "Frank" Preston Blair, Jr., and grandson of Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876), graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy at Annapolis, Maryland, in 1866, being the youngest graduate to complete the full course up until that time. He served in the navy for two years and then resigned because of illness. Blair then became an analytical chemist and was a founding member of the firm of Booth, Garrett and Blair. He was well-known in his field, publishing many papers and reports.
Biography of Blair Lee
Blair Lee (1857-1944), lawyer, legislator and social reformer, was born in Silver Spring, Maryland, the only child of Samuel Phillips Lee and Elizabeth Blair. He was educated at Princeton University (Class of 1880), where he was a founding member and president of the Ivy Club, and at Columbian (now George Washington) Law School earning a law degree in 1883. A practicing attorney in Washington, D.C., and Maryland, Lee also participated in Democratic politics, an interest which had been nurtured by his mother and grandfather, Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876). He was twice elected to the Maryland State Senate (1905 and 1909), and among his accomplishments there was the passage of legislation establishing the primary law for party nominations and the creation of the Maryland State Roads Commission. Although narrowly defeated in 1911 in a race for governor of Maryland, Lee was elected to the United States Senate in 1913, the first senator elected under the 17th Amendment, in a special election following the death of Isidor Rayner. While in the United States Senate, he was active in passing legislation such as the Farm Loan Law, the amending of the Federal Reserve Law, and the Hay-Wadsworth Bill. A delegate to eight Democratic national conventions, he worked actively for the election of William Jennings Bryan (1896 and 1900) and Woodrow Wilson (1912 and 1916).
In 1891 he married Anne Clymer Brooke and, after her death (1903), helped raise their sons, Edward Brooke Lee (1892-1984, Princeton Class 1916) and Phillips Blair Lee (1895-1983, Princeton Class of 1918). Lee's interests included social reform and philanthropy, and he was active in the National Junior Republic, National Mary Washington Memorial Association, and the Washington City Orphan Asylum. He also participated in fraternal groups such as the Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia, the Princeton Class of 1880 and the Ivy Club, and the K.F.R. Society.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the personal and family papers of five members of the Blair and Lee families of Maryland, Washington, D.C., and Virginia -- Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876); his daughter, Elizabeth Blair Lee (1818-1906); her husband, Samuel Phillips Lee (1812-1897); their son, Blair Lee (1857-1944, Princeton Class of 1880); and his cousin, Andrew Alexander Blair (1848-1932) -- reflecting their various political, journalistic, naval, family, business, legal, and domestic interests. While the collection largely pertains to these five family members, their papers also contain a significant amount of correspondence, documents, and writings of other members of the Blair and Lee families. Among other topics, materials in this collection document the families' involvement in American politics spanning from the Jacksonian Era through World War I.
The Blair family papers consist primarily of papers of politician and journalist Francis Preston Blair (1791-1876), including writings and lectures, documents, family correspondence, articles and other materials related to his editorship of the Globe, estate records, and correspondence with prominent political figures, including many involved with the administration of Andrew Jackson. The papers of his daughter, Elizabeth Blair Lee, document the political and social lives of the Blair and Lee families, as well as her work with the Washington City Orphan Asylum. The papers of Blair's grandson, Andrew Alexander Blair, contain additional family correspondence and span his time at the United States Naval Academy prior to becoming a chemist.
The Lee family papers include the papers of Samuel Phillips Lee, which document his service in the United States Navy, including his involvement in the U.S. Coast Survey, as well as the management of the Silver Spring Farm, real estate ventures, and family and domestic life. The papers of his son, the lawyer and politician Blair Lee, relate to his life as a student, work as a lawyer and United States senator during World War I and the administration of Woodrow Wilson, service in various organizations, and personal and family life.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Researchers may be required to use surrogates of collection items stored in special vault facilities. Consult curator for access to originals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were originally deposited at Princeton University Library on August 1, 1942, and later gifted to the university by P. Blair Lee (Class of 1918) and E. Brooke Lee (Class of 1916) in 1965-1969 (AM 21313).
Appraisal
No materials were separated during 2017 processing.
Related Materials
For additional Blair family papers, assembled by other members of the Blair family, refer to:
Blair Family Papers (Princeton University Library, C1569)
Blair Family Papers (Library of Congress, MSS12930)
Administration of estates -- Maryland.; Bimetalism.; City planning -- United States -- 20th century.; Criminal law -- Maryland.; Education -- New Jersey -- 19th century.; Elections -- United States.; English literature -- Study and teaching -- New Jersey -- Princeton -- 19th century.; Estates (Law) -- Maryland.; Fathers and daughters -- Washington (D.C.) -- 19th century.; Fathers and sons -- Maryland.; French spoliation claims.; Governors -- New Jersey -- 20th century.; Husband and wife -- Maryland -- Silver Spring -- 19th century.; Husband and wife -- Washington (D.C.) -- 19th century.; Law -- United States -- Cases.; Local government -- Maryland -- 20th century.; Mothers and sons -- New Jersey -- Princeton -- 20th century.; Municipal government -- Maryland.; Naval education -- Maryland -- Annapolis -- 19th century.; Naval history -- 19th century.; Patronage, Political -- Maryland -- Montgomery County.; Political clubs -- Maryland -- Montgomery County.; Political conventions -- United States.; Politicians -- Maryland.; Politicians -- United States.; Presidents -- United States -- Elections, 1896.; Presidents -- United States -- Elections, 1900.; Presidents -- United States -- Elections, 1908.; Presidents -- United States -- Elections, 1912.; Presidents' spouses -- United States.; Real property -- Maryland -- Montgomery County.; Real property -- Missouri -- St. Louis.; Real property -- Washington (D.C.).; Students and war -- United States -- 19th century.; World War, 1914-1918 -- France -- Photographs.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, American.; Maryland -- Governors -- 19th century.; Maryland -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Maryland -- History -- 1775-1865.; Maryland -- History -- 1865-1950.; Maryland -- Politics and government -- 1861-1865.; Maryland -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865.; Maryland -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; Montgomery County (Md.) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Montgomery County (Md.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History, Naval -- 19th century.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1853-1857.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1857-1861.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1933.; Account books.; Business records.; Campaign literature, 1896; Campaign literature, 1905; Campaign literature, 1909; Campaign literature, 1911; Campaign literature, 1912; Campaign literature, 1913; Campaign speeches, 1852; Campaign speeches, 1856; Campaign speeches, 1896; Campaign speeches, 1911; Campaign speeches, 1912; Case files.; Commonplace books.; Contracts; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Family papers.; Insurance policies.; Leases.; Legal correspondence.; Legal documents.; Military maps.; Nautical charts.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Ships' logs.; Editors -- United States.; Journalists -- Washington (D.C.); Lawyers -- Maryland.; Statesmen -- United States.; American history; American politics and government; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1834 -- Political and social views.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924 -- Career in politics.; Blair family; Lee, Blair,1867-1944.; Lee, Elizabeth Blair,1818-1906.; Lee, Samuel Phillips,1812-1897.; Brooks family.; Gist family.; Lee family.; Columbian Law School.; Democratic National Publishing Company.; Democratic Party (Md.) -- History.; Episcopal Church -- Clergy -- 19th century.; K.F.R. Society.; National Mary Washington Memorial Association.; College of New Jersey (Princeton, N.J.) -- Students.; College of New Jersey (Princeton, N.J.). Class of 1880.; College of New Jersey (Princeton, N.J.). Ivy Club.; Silver Knight-Watchman (Washington, D.C.); Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia.; United States. Congress -- Committees -- 20th century.; United States. Navy Dept. -- Bureau of Equipment and Recruiting.; United States. Navy Dept. -- Bureau of Ordnance and Hydrography.; United States. Navy Dept. -- Bureau of Provisions and Clothing.; United States. Navy Dept. -- Bureau of Yards and Dock Construction.; United States. Navy Dept. -- Mississippi Squadron.; United States. Navy Dept. -- North Atlantic Blockading Squadron.; United States. Navy -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States. Navy -- History -- 19th century.; United States. Navy -- Officers -- 19th century.; United States Naval Academy -- Alumni -- 19th century.; Washington City Orphan Asylum.; Brandywine (Ship); Dolphin (Ship); Legare (Ship); Marion (Ship); Nautilus (Ship); Newborn (Ship); Oneida (Ship); Severn (Ship); Vandalia (Ship); Vincennes (Ship); Washington (Ship); Young Rover (Ship)
- Papers of Francis Preston Blair, 1640-1911; 1791-1876; 54 boxes (1 partial)
  Scope and Contents
  The papers of Francis Preston Blair, journalist and politician, consist of writings, correspondence, documents, materials regarding Blair as a subject, printed matter, papers of other persons, and additional papers. The writings include his speeches, editorials, addresses, articles, essays, and general works; these date from 1830, when Blair was called to Washington, D.C., by President Andrew Jackson to edit the Globe, the official newspaper of the Democratic administration. Although he never held an elected office, Blair was considered a person of political importance and influence in the mid-19th century, and his correspondence is indicative of this, containing letters from Andrew Jackson (1767-1845), Martin Van Buren (1782-1862), and Andrew Johnson (1808-1875), as well as senators Lewis Cass (1782-1866), John Charles Fremont (1813-1890), and John Jordan Crittenden (1787-1863), and congressmen Schuyler Colfax (1823-1885), Edward Livingston (1764-1836), and Thomas Patrick Moore (1797-1853).
  Also included is family correspondence, especially with his sons, Francis "Frank" Preston Blair, Jr. (1821-1875, Princeton Class of 1841), lawyer, general, and politician, and Montgomery Blair (1813-1883), lawyer, statesman, and postmaster general in President Abraham Lincoln's cabinet, and daughter, Elizabeth Blair Lee, wife of Admiral Samuel Phillips Lee and mother of Blair Lee.
  In addition, there are documents including Blair's last will and testament, financial papers such as receipts, checks, checkbooks, and account books. Among papers of others persons, there is correspondence of Andrew Jackson, manuscripts contributed to the Globe, and old family papers, many of them relating to the family of Eliza Violet Gist, Blair's wife.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by genre of material.
  - Writings, 1830-1869; 2 boxes
    Contains addresses, speeches, tracts, articles, essays, and notes dealing with political subjects including the elections of 1852 and 1856, repeal of the Missouri Compromise, the reviving of the Democratic Party, and the Civil War, as well as politicians such as Andrew Jackson, John C. Calhoun, and Sam Houston. Some of Blair's articles were written for the Globe, which he edited.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - General Writings, circa 1830 - 1840; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes writings regarding drafts for articles in the Globe.
    - General Writings, 1840s - 1860s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Writings about Andrew Jackson, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Monument for Andrew Jackson, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Writings: resignation of Jackson's cabinet, 1831; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Nullification and secession of South Carolina, 1832; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Vs. U.S. Bank, 1831-1833; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - History of the Bank of England, 1830s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - On Calhoun, 1840s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - On American Indians, 1840s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Request to Congress for relief of Mrs. A. Jackson, Jr, circa 1845; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Deposition on political principles of John W. James: after 1836, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Remarks on death of Silas Wright, 1847; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Speech for Sam Houston, 1848; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - About General William O. Butler, 1847-1852; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Election of 1852, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Address at dinner honoring Kossuth, circa 1852 January; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Addresses and letters in election of 1856, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Pittsburgh address, 1856 February 22; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Public letter denouncing Buchanan - Southern conspiracy, 1856 July 24; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Speech for J. C. Fremont, 1856; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Various tracts condemning repeal of Missouri Compromise, 1856; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letter to New York Evening Post, 1856; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letter to New York Tribune: controversy over last sentiments of T. H. Benton toward Buchanan, 1858; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ruin of the Democratic Party, circa 1859; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Meshack Browning", 1860; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Speech or tract, 1861; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Writings: Civil War period, 1862; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Article: Truckling to the South (Civil War), undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Speech vs. the radicals, circa 1868; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Essay vs. annexation of San Domingo, circa 1869; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript notes, lists and fragments, 1830-1833; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Manuscripts of others in the hand of F. P. B., 1842; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1816-1876; 22 boxes
    Contains mainly letters to Blair by members of his family, such as his wife, Eliza Violet Gist Blair, daughter, Elizabeth Blair Lee, sons, Montgomery, James, and Francis "Frank" Preston, Jr., as well as other family members. Also included are letters by people in government, politics, journalism, and the military, such as Andrew Jackson Donelson, William Henry Haywood, John Bigelow, James C. Pickett, John Albion Andrew, and John C. Rives, as well as many ordinary citizens. Also included are some drafts of letters written by Blair.
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - Unidentified and Partial Signatures - Correspondence, 1831-1834; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified Writers Correspondence, 1835-1868; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Writers Correspondence, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Unknown Recipients Correspondence, 1831-1869; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A - Abert, 1835-1867; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Adams, George, 1831-1843; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Adams & Faulkner - Alexander, A. J., 1831-1875; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Alexander, Eveline (Mrs. A. J.), 1862-1868; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Alexander, George M. - Alexander, William, 1831-1864; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Allen, Eliza Claggett (Mrs. Ethan), 1861-1868; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Allen, Ethan, 1861-1870; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Allen, J. - Anderson, 1831-1869; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Andrew, John Albion (1818-1867), 1862-1866; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Andrews - Austin, 1831-1863; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - B - Banks, 1831-1867; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Barbour, John Strode (1790-1855), 1831; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Barker - Bayne, 1831-1869; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Beale - Bicknell, 1830-1868; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bigelow, John (1817-1911), 1852-1867; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Biggs - Blagdon, 1834-1873; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Blair (miscellaneous), 1832-1869; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. Frank P.), undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Blair, Apolline (Mrs. Frank P.), 1847-1873; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Blair, Elizabeth (b. 1841), 1858-1870; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Blair, Eliza Violet Gist (Mrs. F. P., Sr.), 1837-1865; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Blair, Francis P., Jr., 1835-1873; 4 folders
      - Blair, Francis P., Jr., undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Blair, Francis P., Jr., 1835-1851; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Blair, Francis P., Jr., 1852-1859; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Blair, Francis P., Jr., 1860-1873; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Blair, James (1762-1837), father, 1831-1835; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Blair, James, 1831-1834; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Blair, James D, 1837-1858; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Blair, James Lawrence (1819-1853), 1838-1852; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Blair, Minna E. (Mrs. Montgomery), undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Blair, Montgomery, 1831-1863; 6 folders
      - Blair, Montgomery: Letters from F. P. B., Letters to F. P. B, 1836-1863; undated; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Blair, Montgomery: Letters to F. P. B, 1831-1838; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Blair, Montgomery: Letters to F. P. B, 1839-1843; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Blair, Montgomery: Letters to F. P. B, 1844-1854; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Blair, Montgomery: Letters to F. P. B, 1855-1860; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Blair, Montgomery: Letters to F. P. B, 1861-1872; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Blake - Bowman, 1855-1860; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Bradford - Brown, 1861-1872; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Browning - Burton, 1831-1866; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Butler to Bynum, 1831-1865; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 2)